General
将軍！
They retreated too quickly
彼ら、撤退が早すぎて
Didn't catch them all
全員を捕らえ得ず
Prince of Jin
晋王……
That rabbit emperor in the south
南のあの“ウサギ皇帝”が
Has raised a wolf
狼を育てたか
Just lost some tents
帷帳を多少失ったに過ぎぬ
General Shi's fifty thousand troops
石将軍の五万大軍
No matter how he schemes
彼がいかに策を練ろうとも
It's just
ただ
A breeze brushing fur
そよ風が羽毛を撫でるほどのもの
What do you know?
何を知るか
When two armies fight
両軍の戦は
It's all about momentum
勢いこそ命！
The Xuan people's arrows
宣人の矢は
Have almost all been used on the refugees
流民にほぼ使い果たされ申した
Call the craftsmen
工匠が作った
The finished catapults
投石機を移動せよ
At dawn
明け方に
Send two units
二隊を
To attack the city in rotation
交替で城を攻め立てよ
On the other side
また
Work faster too
速やかに作業を進めよ
Yes
承知！
Send people out of the city
兵士を遣わし
To recover arrows as much as possible
出城して矢を回収せよ
At the same time
同時に
Open the southern grain storehouse
城南の穀倉を開いて
Reward our troops for the successful raid
奇襲の勝利を讃え
Have the soldiers
将士を
Celebrate together
慰労せよ
Yes
承知！
This General Zhu
朱将軍
Truly has the courage of a bear and tiger
まさに虎と熊の如く勇猛だよ！
I saw in the Wuzhao camp
鄔奴の陣地が
Flames reaching the sky
火花散り
Truly satisfying
痛快この上なし！
Pity
惜しむは
Only good food
飯のみで
No wine
酒なしか
I think
だがこれ
This meal is like a last meal
断頭飯の如し
Zhu Yuanzhi showed off
朱元之が威を示せば
Won't the Wuzhao retaliate?
鄔奴も報復を企てるぞ
Maybe they'll launch a full attack tonight
今夜にも総攻めかもしれん…
Lately I
数日
Can't sleep well
眠れず
Always hear
夢に
Thumping sounds
「ドドド」の轟音
Always dream of Wuzhao warhorses
鄔奴の大馬に
Trampling down on me
踏み潰される夢を見申す
Shut up and eat
飯を食え
Stop thinking about this and that
余計なことは考えず
Scaring yourself
己を怖がらせるな！
Although we've repelled the enemy
退けたりとはいえ
But arrows are exhausted
矢尽き
All kinds of weapons and traps
罠や兵器も
Are also severely depleted
消耗甚だし
Also
さらに
Need to immediately assign people
人手を調え
To urgently repair the city walls
城壁の補修に努めねば
How many men do we have left?
残りの人数は？
Heavy casualties
死傷甚だしく
Now only about two thousand can still fight
戦えるは二千余
If the Wuzhao attack again
鄔奴軍が再度攻め来らば
At most we can
二日が
Hold for two days
限度に候…
Report
報ぜり！
There's an army to the south
城南にわが
Approaching us
軍へ向かう部隊見ゆ
They don't look like Wuzhao
鄔奴人には見えず
Chen Ying's reinforcements have arrived
陳応の援軍か？
Let's go take a look
行こう、見届けよ！
Who goes there?
何者だ？
I'm Liu Dadao
我は劉大刀！
Commander of Yong'an Garrison's Left Army
永安城の守備左軍の統領なり
These
これらは
Are all the lords of northern fortresses
北地の各鄔堡領主
Zhang, Huang, Liu, Li
張・黄・劉・李
The four great families
四大家族も
Have also come
伴い参る
Although we're in the north
我ら北地にあれど
In our hearts
心は
We always recognize the Xuan on this flag
常にこの旗の“宣”を認む！
Everyone heard the royal army is trapped in Yiyang
王師が弋陽城に包囲と聞き及び
Specially led the northern volunteer army
北地義軍を率いて
To come and help
来援奉る！
Great Xuan's old subjects
大宣旧民
Willing to die for Great Xuan
命を賭して忠誠を尽くさん！
It's reinforcements
援軍だ！
Our reinforcements
我らの援軍だ！
Your Highness
殿下
Look
いかがでしょう？